SIGHT AND SOUND / DAVID McCUNE 
The Shape (and Color) Of Things to Come 
PC MAGAZINE • MAY I. 1984 • pp. 191-211


* Color mapping, blink-based animation, and other visual treats can be accomplished on your PC, thanks to four new products that create and display graphics with NAPLPS code. *

The heart of data communication is consensus, not technology. All of the cables, modems, and microwave hops on earth ate useless if the sender and receiver disagree on how to interpret the data being sent. Fortunately, such a consensus does exist, at least for text. Nearly all microcomputer manufacturers have an agreement that certain bytes, when sent to a screen or printer, will be displayed the same way. This agreement is called ASCII, the American Standard Code for Information Interchange. But suppose you want to send a command for “circle” or “line” or "blue”? You’re in trouble. There is no accepted way to encode a pie chart on an IBM PC and have it appear as anything better than lemon meringue on an Apple 11. 

More than any other problem, this lack of a standard has inhibited the spread of graphics applications for micros. Graphics software developed for one micro often has to be almost completely rewritten before it will mn on another brand of micro. And unlike textual databases like CompuServe — which use the ASCII standard — graphics databases would have to be specific to a particular kind of micro. Hope exists, though, in the form of NAPLPS (nap-lips, as the cognoscenti like to say), the North American Presentation Level Protocol Syntax. NAPLPS holds promise as a standard for two reasons: It can be used as a standard for encoding and displaying graphics in similar ways on different machines, and it compresses complex graphic images — such as circles, lines, and polygons — into short strings of bytes, making it an effi-cient way to store and transmit graphics.

Like any standard, NAPLPS will ultimately be judged by the number of con-verts it can claim. Some heavy hitters have already jumped on the wagon; these include AT&T, TimesMinor Corpora-tion, Knight-Ridder, and Cox Communications. Scores of NAPLPS software pro-grams and hardware vendors have emerged in the past few years. Current applications range from mass-market NAPLPS databases to placement of small database systems in shopping malls, hotels, and airports. NAPLPS graphics are also being used for business presentations and computer-aided instruction. (For a brief discussion of NAPLPS features and terminology, sec sidebar, “A NAPLPS Primer and Glossary.”)


* NAPLPS Comes to Your PC *

Until very recently, PC owners could not use their micros to tap into NAPLPS. NAPLPS graphics were created and displayed on expensive standalone “frame-creation’ ’ workstations and decoder terminals. In the past few months, though, PC-based products for displaying, creating. and organizing NAPLPS frames have appeared. This review will look at four of those products.

On the most rudimentary level, graph-ics display software must place graphic images in the proper place on the screen and display the images in the proper colors. NAPLPS defines a rich variety of graphic shapes, including geometric prim-itives like “point,” “line,” “rectangle,” and “polygon,” alphanumeric characters, rectangular mosaics that can be pieced together into complex images, and non-ASCII alphabetic characters (such as special German or Danish characters). In addition, NAPLPS uses color mapping to set each dot on the video screen to one of a large number of colors. A PC equipped with the standard IBM graphics adapter is perfectly capable of displaying all NAPLPS graphic shapes correctly. Since the graphics adapter does not use color-mapping technology, though, and only displays four colors simultaneously, it is not possible to write full NAPLPS decoding software for this hardware. Even most non-IBM color boards — such as Plantronics' COLOR-PLUS — can only display a predefined set of 16 colors.


** MVI: A Videotex Interpreter **

If you want to take advantage of NAPLPS extensive drawing capabilities and can live with limited color capability, Microstar Software Ltd. offers a creditable software NAPLPS decoder to be used with the PC. 

The Microstar Videotex Interpreter (MVI) can display NAPLPS graphics either from a floppy disk or ftom a remote NAPLPS database. MV! can also download videotex fhimes ftom remote databases for storage on your local disk, upload videotex frames to other computers, and print graphic renderings of NAPLPS frames on Epson and IDS Prism printers. You can also use MV! in a non-NAPLPS dumb terminal mode to access and retrieve data ftom ASCII databases like CompuServe.

MVI is delivered on one copy-protected disk, along with a manual. 1 found the copy-protection scheme worrisome, especially since the MVI writes to the disk dur-ing use (to update a table of communications parameters set by the user). Microstar should provide at least one backup, rather than simply assuring me that I can replace a damaged master disk “for a nominal fee upon receipt of the original.” In spite of the copy protection, MVI will ran on the hard disk or RAM-disk. To tun MVI from, say, drive C, you need to copy the master-disk files to drive C and then, with the master disk in drive A, ran C:MVI. MVI will check that drive A contains a true master disk, after which you are free to replace it with, say, a data disk.

MVI requires an IBM PC (or XT) or compatible. (Microstar advertises Compaq and Columbia compatibility. I ran the program on both a Compaq and an IBM PC.) You need 192K RAM. one 320K disk drive, an IBM color adapter or Plan-tronics COLORPLUS card, a color monitor, one asynchronous communications adapter, and a modem (if you want to access remote databases).

* Manual Labor *

If you, like I, have an allergy to manuals and prefer just to put in a new disk and crank up the software, you’ll be in trouble. The documentation falls into the category “OK once you know how the program works.” The manual starts with a half-hearted tutorial designed to log you on to a videotex database. This led to a confusing message: Communications Parameters. I was told to refer to an Appendix G (which was missing) for help in filling in the necessary values. Some parameters (baud rate, parity, and so on) were familiar, but others (XOR, CTRL, PHONE, LOGON) are specific to MVI and are only explained deep inside the manual.

[ Illustrations ]
	1. Full-blown NAPLPS frame, displayed through standalone decoder in RGB video. (Time Video Information Services.)

	2. With a Plantronics COLORPLUS board. Microstar's software NAPLPS interpreter (MVl) modifies some original colors, but produces a creditable reproduction -

	3. MVI pares the original down to four colors on IBM's color graphics adapter (palette 0. green, red. brown and a black background). Note that upper deck of ship disappears into background.

	4. The composite video output of the IBM color graphics adapter is almost useless if you need to read text.

	5. MVI switches easily to IBM's second default palette (cyan, magenta, while).

	6. We can change MVl's default assignment of IBM colors to NAPLPS colors and improve the display. Note that the upper deck has reap-peared.

Since most fust-time users will be more anxious to see if MV! really displays snaz-zy NAPLPS graphics than in running through a short course in data communications, Microstar should pro-vide a few sample NAPLPS frames on the master disk along with a tutorial on the relatively simple procedure for displaying those files.

* Great Shapes * 

The manual again refers to Appendix G for a list of available NAPLPS databases. If it had been there, it would have been helpful. After struggling through the tutorial, 1 connected to Grassroots, a huge NAPLPS database in Winnipeg, where 1 have an account. Bingo! A full-blown NAPLPS frame appeared on my color monitor (and in shades of green on my internal Compaq monitor).

* The problem with color translation rests with IBM’s limited color capabilities and not with MVI. *

I noticed two things immediately. First, the NAPLPS geometric shapes decoded perfectly. This is no small feat. I have seen a number of supposedly “finished” soft-ware NAPLPS interpreters, and even a couple of standalone decoders, display all kinds of bizarre, incorrect shapes. (There is even a term, “exploding PDIs,” for what some poor decoders do to the Picture Description Instructions that make up NAPLPS frames.)

Second, the colors were weird. Grass-roots uses up to 16 colors simultaneously (drawn from a total palette of thousands of possible colors) on each frame. Since the IBM color adapter can display only four colors at any one time, MVt had to trans-late some of the Grassroots colors into one of four IBM colors. Grassroots' blue, for example, turned into IBM red. Seeing familiar Grassroots screens like this was about as disconcerting as seeing an IBM salesman in madras pants.

 But, oh, what a sense of liberation! Equipped with only a standard PC, free of my $1,600 outboard NAPLPS decoder, 1 was accessing an extraordinary world of graphics not originally designed with the IBM PC in mind.

Since receiving MVI, I have displayed hundreds of NAPLPS frames, including some I created myself to test how MVI handles some of NAPLPS’ more exotic features. Microstar told me MVI would correctly decode all NAPLPS except col-or-map manipulations (which includes “phased blink”), Dynamically Redefinable Character Sets (DRCS), which lets the user create up to 96 customized charac-ters, and unprotected fields. With one major and several minor exceptions. MVI works as advertised.

Polygons, lines, rectangles, arcs, and dots all appear correctly, even when combined with the four NAPLPS default fill patterns and line textures. Every screen from Grassroots seemed fine in this regard, along with all my home-grown test frames. The only errors I found occurred in a few complex screens produced by artists at Time, Inc. , in New York City. Sev-eral polygons were shifted away from their correct positions. (Since these frames had been produced on a non-NAPLPS terminal and translated into NAPLPS by Tirrie, Inc.’s conversion software, it is possible that the problem is with the frames, rather than with MVI.)

With one important exception, text characters appear in the right size and place, even when subjected to exotic NAPLPS scaling and rotation commands. A serious flaw occurs, though, when a string of text contains a carriage return and linefeed. In NAPLPS, like ASCII, these bytes should force the cursor down one line to the left margin. MVI uses compiled BASIC for disk I/O, and since BASIC uses the carriage retum/linefeed sequence to mark “end of record,” these two bytes ate never passed to the NAPLPS interpret-er. (The solution is to set the eighth bit of each byte to one. Microstar promises such a utility program in future releases.) Since it is common for NAPLPS artists to begin each new line of text with an explicit “set drawing point” command, rather than relying on the carriage retum/linefeed sequence, this bug does not show up often. In some databases, though, the bug could severely distort many pages.

* MVI was able to decode the NAPLPS geometric shapes perfectly, but the colors were weird. *

The NAPLPS supplemental character set, which includes many non-English alphabetics, displays correctly, and NAPLPS’ powerful macro capabilities perform well. In fact, other than the non-supported features mentioned earlier, 1 could find only a few things that did not work: user-defined texture patterns, the mosaic character set, the incremental point, line and polygon features, propor-tional spacing, underlining (which works intermittently), and visible cursor (though Microstar says a box cursor is available in a new release).

Microstar’s manual doesn’t mention it, but MVI will only work with 7-bit NAPLPS. Although nearly all NAPLPS databases use the 7-bit variant of the stan-dard, there’s one important exception. Viewtron, the Knight-Ridder database in Florida, is an 8-bit NAPLPS database. This is one of the best videotex databases around, and MVI will not allow you to access it.

* Color Definition *

The problem with color translation rests with IBM’s limited color capabilities and not with MVI, which performs as advertised. NAPLPS can produce a nearly unlimited variety of colors that can be mapped into a theoretically huge color table. In fact, most standalone decoders allow for 16 simultaneous colors, chosen from a palette of 512. IBM, in contrast, supplies only two palettes of three prede-fined colors: green, red, and brown in pal-ette O; and cyan, magenta, and white in palette 1. Including a background color (which MVI always sets to black) each IBM display has four possible colors.

MVI translates NAPLPS color definitions into IBM colors through a two-step process. First, the software creates an imaginary color table of 16 colors, corresponding to 16 default NAPLPS colors (an 8-level gray scale, plus blue, magenta, red, yellow, green, and cyan, with two of the 16 slots unused). Next, each of the 16 slots is assigned one of the four IBM pal-ette entries. As it reads a new NAPLPS color defintion, MVI first determines which of the default NAPLPS colors is the best match. It then checks the IBM color associated with this default NAPLPS color and sets the proper part of the display to this color.

It does not take much for a low-key NAPLPS page to appear either garish or illegible. Using MVI's normal assignment of IBM colors to NAPLPS colors, for example, a green NAPLPS rectangle on a dark gray background would appear as a green rectangle on a green background — invisible! Fortunately, the user has some control over the color display. First, MVI lets you quickly switch between the two IBM pal-ettes at any time during a display. While this will not make invisible graphics reap-pear, it does often make ugly frames more — uh — palatable . I found myself con-stantly switching back and forth (by pres-sing the F6 key) as I displayed screens.

MVI also allows you to change the cor-respondence between IBM colors and each of the 16 default NAPLPS colors. If you are not happy with dark gray showing up as green or cyan on your PC monitor, for example, you can assign one of the other three PC colors to the dark gray slot. To do so, you choose “Colour Table” from the “Communications Parameters” submenu. The 16-slot color table appears as two rows of eight colored boxes. The boxes are IBM colors, and each one rep-resents one of the NAPLPS default cotors. Bizarrely, MVI does not tell you which IBM color box represents which NAPLPS color. Discovering that information re-quired making a phone call to Ottawa.

* MVI is particularly attractive for applications where graphics are created with its color limitations in mind. *

While graphics may occasionally dis-appear into their backgrounds, MVI offers a handy feature that increases the chance that text will be visible. On the “Communications Parameters” display, the user can turn on something called “XOR.” When XOR is on, MVI exam-ines each pixel of a text character and ' ‘ex-clusively-or” its color bits with the color bits of the background color. Green text on a green background, for example, will be changed to black text on a green back-ground.

In spite of all these potential color prob-lems, I was surprised at how seldom I ran into indecipherable frames. A few minutes of twiddling color table entries invariably improved the picture. I can certainly con-ceive of NAPLPS frames that would be almost useless when viewed through MVI's filter — an advertisement for paint, for example — but the vast majority of frames were useful, if not always aesthet-ically pleasing.

I strongly recommend that you use an RGB monitor with your IBM color graph-ics adapter. IBM’s composite video signal is scandalously bad, and small NAPLPS letters often “bleed” to the point of illeg-ibility. MVI also runs with a Plantronics COL-ORPLUS board. The 1 6 simultaneous col-ors on the COLORPLUS board overcome many of IBM’s graphics adapter’s color problems.

* Hidden Treasures *

MVI is more than a NAPLPS decoder, though you have to read the manual pretty closely to discover its other features. First, it can be used as a general communica-tions package. You can define a specific set of communications parameters for each of many databases you use. These may be NAPLPS or ASCII databases, since MVl can also be put into ASCII dumb terminal mode. Once you have defined a database, its name will appear in a list of available databases whenever you start up MVl.

Besides the normal communication characteristics (speed, parity, and so on) MVl also has a keyboard utility that lets you define the string of characters you want your modem to dial in order to con-nect to the database, the color table to be used with this database, and character strings to be attached to each of the ten PC function keys. I have defined Grassroots as database 1 in my directory of databases, for example. Once 1 start up MVl. 1 press two keys to get MVl to dial the local Tym-net phone number, identify itself to Tym-net, input the 17-digit Tymnet/Datapac address for Grassroots, select the proper Datapac channel, and coimect to Grass-roots. And I have defined the F2 key to enter my Grassroots user ID, and F3 to enter my password.

MV! can upload and download files between your PC and a remote computer. These file transfers use a simple XON/ XOPT^ protocol with no error checking. Both directions wotk fine, though you feel like Houdini once you’ve figured out how to do it. Transfers are initiated by pressing the Ctrl key and one of the function keys. There is no menu and no on-line help.

* Getting It down on Paper *

As you look at a NAPLPS graphic, you can also print it on either an Epson printer (in shades of gray) or an IDS Prism printer (in color). 1 tested only the Epson print program. How impressive the graphics output is depends on the colots in the orig-inal frame. Some of the printouts were good enough for “oohs” and “aahs” from friends. I also ran MV! with a public-domain graphics printing program for the Okidata 92, with good results. If you don't have a graphics printer, MV! will still print the extracted text from any NAPLPS frame on a plain ASCII printer. This is useful if you want to quick-ly print a news story or a stock market listing. 1 used this feature to print the text from a series of instruction screens for one NAPLPS database.

All in all, I am pleased with MVI's per-formance. With minor exceptions, it lives up to its claims. It is an inexpensive way to display nearly any NAPLPS graphic. MV! is particularly attractive for applications where graphics are created with its color limitations in mind. Used in conjunction with a NAPLPS frame-creation unit (such as Picture Painter, which is reviewed below), MVl could be a great tool for dis-playing and disseminating business or even mass-market graphics packages. The MVl staff, particularly president Peter Jordan, who wrote most of the pro-gram, was extraordinarily helpful. Never did I hear “Oh, you’re doing it wrong” when 1 called to report bugs. Microstar appears to care about its customers.

MVI's greatest obstacle is its own poor documentation and user interface. This is a difficult package to use. The need for on-line help and much better prompting is essential. Now that the bulk of the NAPLPS decoding work is done, I hope the folks at Microstar invest more energy in improving the lot of the inexperienced user.


** Quickpel: A Complete NAPLPS Interpreter **

Some users, graphic artists, say, may not be happy with the limita-tions imposed by software decod-ers that rely entirely on standard IBM hardware. Some of the snazziest NAPLPS features — for instance, color mapping and phased blink, which can be used for ani-mation — just can’t be produced with an IBM graphics adapter. Until now, the only alternative has been to connect a standalone decoder to your computer either via phone or an RS-232 cable. Such decoders generally cost around $1,500.

An extraordinary new plug-in PC board changes all this. Quickpel is a complete NAPLPS interpreter that fits into one PC expansion slot. It receives NAPLPS bytes over the PC bus — either from disk or from a remote site via a separate asynchronous adapter — and produces a composite video signal which you feed into your color monitor.

As if full NAPLPS interpretation were not enough, Quickpel also lets you load non-NAPLPS program codes onto the board. These programs — known as ‘ ‘tele-software” — can be interspersed with NAPLPS and can access and manipulate the entire bit map and color table. The ramifications for NAPLPS appli-cations are enormous. Quickpel combines the advantages of compact and standard NAPLPS encoding with the high-speed animation possible from direct control of the screen’s bit map.

I used Quickpel in both a PC and a Compaq, The manufacturer, a new com-pany called Micropixel, Inc., assures me the board will run in an XT and the Eagle as well. The board 1 used was a prototype, but both the hardware and software were cleaner than on many finished products I’ve seen. Production units were sched-uled for delivery during the second week of March. Installation was straightforward; Quickpel plugged into one expansion slot. The prototype was a couple of millimeters too long, so I popped the plastic card guide off my Compaq to make room.

[ Illustration ]
	Grassroots, an agricultural database In Winnipeg, Canada, produced these NAPLPS frames for merchandise ordering, merchandise Information, weather reports, market reports for agricultural products, and season’s greetings. From left to right: Infomart’s weather report, Timex, Inc., ad. Manitoba Cattle Producers Assoc. 's market report, advertisement tor the LP "The Bay Windows,” and seasons greetings from Grassroots.

The prototype unit produced only com-posite video, which was accessed from a phono plug. A PCyr-like RF connector is planned for production units, so Quickpel can be used with a standard color TV set. I groaned upon hearing that no RGB output was planned: visions of the fuzzy, often illegible characters produced by the IBM color adapter’s composite signal raced through my mind. And indeed, when 1 first powered up the computer with Quick-pel installed, I groaned again. A fuzzy, wavy greenish yellow blob intruded on the upper left comer of the blank monitor screen. But then I pumped one NAPLPS frame into Quickpel. Wow! Kudos to the video engineeis. Quickpel produces one of the cleanest, sharpest composite signals I’ve seen. From that moment on, I never missed the RGB output.

* Full NAPLPS Interpretation * 

Hearing a vendor claim his product is full NAPLPS is a bit like listening to someone tell you he never broke the law. “Never even drove 56 mph?” you ask. “OK," he admits, “but that’s not really breaking the law...” Quickpel seems true to its claim, though. In the 24 hours I had the board, I tried every exotic NAPLPS string I could invent. Everything worked perfectly. Blink, color mapping. textures, cursor manipulation, character scaling, macros, mosaics, supplemental characters — all 100 percent. 1 certainly didn’t exhau.st all po.s$ible permutations of NAPLPS commands in the short time 1 had the board, but Quickpel didn’t suffer from any of the problems common to oth-er NAPLPS decoders. If complete adher-ence to the NAPLPS standard were impor-tant to me (which it is), I would pick the Quickpel board as my decoder (which 1 will).

Quickpel produces a common NAPLPS screen resolution of 256 by 200, and it displays 16 simultaneous colors from a palette of 512. Quickpel comes with a DOS 2.0 device driver. Once installed, displaying NAPLPS frames is as easyas“CX)PY <file>QPEL:.’’ PC pro-grams can access QPEL like any normal DOS device. In addition to the driver, Quickpel comes with V7X, a commu-nications program disk for access to remote computers. When you use VTX, all keyboard input is sent out through an asynchronous adapter, and all input to the comm port is directed to Quickpel. The prerelease version of VTX also allowed for a dumb terminal mode so that incoming data would display on the monochrome monitor. File transfers of N.APLPS data also worked well.

The NAPLPS interpretation is handled by an Intel 8088 (the same microprocessor that mns your PC) on the Quickpel board. Ingeniously, the 8088 is controlled by a multitasking executive, which doles out processor time to tire NAPLPS interpreter task and any other task that wants atten-tion. This “other task’’’ can make full use of Quickpel’s RAM, including the bit map and the color map. It could even produce its own NAPLPS code and send it to the NAPLPS interpretation task for execution. The 8088 machine code for these non-NAPLPS tasks can be loaded into Quick-pel much like standard NAPLPS code. Various “escape sequences” teU the exec-utive whether incoming bytes are NAPLPS or machine code. RAM includes 64K for the bit map and NAPLPS scratch pad and 16K for telesoft-ware code and data. The NAPLPS inter-preter is stored in 80K bytes of ROM, and telesoftware and communications man-agement occupies another I6K bytes of ROM. (Quickpel also includes 256 bytes of EEPROM, so small amounts of data (like the user’s name, or a database's phone number) can be stored even when the PC is shut off.

* Writing programs for Quickpel is as easy as writing for your PC’s 8088. *

Two demo programs supplied with Quickpel showed the enormous potential for telesoftware applications. One prt)-gram drew colored lines of gradually vary-ing lengths on the screen, producing a kaleidoscopic effect. The screen manipu-lation was much faster and more complex than anything that can be done with a NAPLPS interpreter. The second program produced a “pseudosprite.” First, a nor-mal NAPLPS page full of graphics and text was displayed. Then, a small rectan-gle began to zip across the screen from left to right. Each time the rectangle moved, the portion of the screen that had been overwritten was restored to its original State. This type of fast, nondestructive ani-mation is not possible with normal NAPLPS decoders, which caimot save portions of the bit map for later restora-tion.

Since the 8088 executive is multitask-ing, it is possible to run, say, a telesoft-ware task concurrently with a NAPLPS decoding task. I tried displaying a NAPLPS frame while running the kalei-doscopic demo. The effect was bizarre: As the executive switched back atrd forth between tasks, interwoven pieces of each of the two graphics were displayed.

Writing programs for Quickpel is as easy as writing for your PC’s 8088. Pro-grams must be .COM flies and can be assembled (or compiled) and linked on the PC. The fmished program is then loaded onto Quickpel with a “telesoftware load-er” provided with the board. The Quick-pel documentation, which was sketchy during the prototype phase, includes a pro-grammer’s description of the board (that is, a irremoty map), a list of software inter-rupts, and tte like. Micropbtel is also con-sidering selling a “programmer’s tool-box” for the board, which will include libraries of assembler subroutines to facil-itate access to executive calls, I/O routines for various languages, and NAPLPS cod-ing routines.

All of this wonderful telesoftware raises a problem. NAPLPS is valuable precisely because it is a standard. NAPLPS says nothing, however, about telesoftware. Users must be aware that as soon as they include telesoftware in the stream of bytes they send to a decoder, then they are limited to one make of decoder, that is, the Quickpel (or its stand-alone cousin, the EGT-100 by Electro-home, Ltd.). Even if Micropixel can con-vince the various standards committees that telesoftware is a wonderful extension of NAPLPS, true standards are probably years away.

In summary, Quickpel is a great product that combines the advantages of a first-class NAPLPS decoder with the power and flexibility of a programmable color-mapped video display board. Whether you simply want to display NAPLPS graphics or write sophisticated graphics application programs, it is hard to beat the power and convenience of Quickpel. And the price is lower than most standalone NAPLPS decoders.


** Picture Painter: A Frame Creation System **

When you get tired of looking at other people’s NAPLPS pages, you can create your own on your PC. Picture Painter is a pow-erfull NAPLPS creation system that holds its own — in performance, if not in docu-mentation — against much more expensive standalone competitors.

The minimum system configuration for Picture Painter is pricey. You need a PC with at least one 320K drive, 128K RAM, two asynchronous adapters, a Summagra-phics Bit Pad One tablet, a color monitor, and a staixlalone NAPLPS decoder. Cableshare will fix you up with the last three items for about $4,200, though you’d probably save money buying them on your own.

Your choice of decoder is important. Since most decoders on the market only display a subset of NAPLPS, you can eas-ily And yourself in a bind where your Pic-ture Painter encodes graphics that your decoder can’t display. I used a Norpak Mark IV Videotex Decoder for this review and found that it could not display uixler-lined text, user-defined textures, or phase blink correctly, even though the Picture Painter could produce them. A Quickpel/ Picture Painter combination would be an ideal setup, though Cableshare will have to adapt its software to run with Quick-pel’s device driver.

* A NAPLPS Primer and Glossary *

Here’s a brief key to help you decode basic NAPLPS concepts and terminology. Like too many computerites, NAPLPS converts tend to bombard one another with esoteric terminology. This brief NAPLPS primer and glossary may help you return some of the fire.

NAPLES (North American Presen-tation Level Protocol Syntax): A pro-posed set of rules for encoding and decoding computer graphics instmc-tions. If lots of graphics hardware and software manufacturers agree to interpret NAPLPS instructions, then NAPLPS will become a graphics “standard.”

To understand one of NAPLPS’s greatest strengths — its compactness — imagine that you had to describe to a friend on the phone how to draw a pic-ture of a red ball on a green rectangle. Suppose you start with the instruction “pick up the green pen,” and then say, “Draw a solid rectangle that goes from the upper left-most square to the lower right-most square on the page.” You then tell him to “pick up the red pen.” And then you say, “Draw a circle with a diameter stretching from X-Y coordinate 1(X), 100 to coordinate 200, 100. ” If your fiiend is smart enough to understand ideas like “rectangle” and “circle,” you’ll get your drawing with just a few instructions and a few seconds on the phone.

NAPLPS takes this approach. It con-sists of strings of coimnands like “set color” and “draw rectangle.” A NAPLPS decoder must be smart enough (that is, it must contain enough program-ming) to turn the abstract NAPLPS instmctions into the thousands of indi-vidual bits that produce the graphic dis-play on your computer’s C!RT.

The key is that the instructions trans-mitted to the computer are very con-densed and abstract. Also, the instructions themselves are independent of any particular computer. In other wtxds, as long as someone writes NAPLPS decoding software for ma-chines like the IBM PC and the Apple lie, then the same string of NAPLPS can produce the same graphic display on both machines. (Hardware differences still cause trouble, though. NAPLPS can define an orange rectangle, even though the PC can’t display orange. The PC would have to substitute one of its avail-able colors — red, say — while another more sc^ihisticated color computer might really display an orange rectangle.)

Besides the basic geometric shapes (point, line, arc, rectangle, polygon), NAPLPS defines hundreds of other graphic commands, ranging ftom the normal alphabetic characters to Eun^ an character sets and more. (You can get official, complete NAPLPS specifications by sending $20 plus $4 handling to the American National Standards Institute, 1430 Broadway, New York, NY 10018, Attn: Sales Department. Specify Document X3.110 when ordering.)

Given these background concepts and the following definitions, you should be able to make sense out of NAPLPS talk.

Pixel: Short for “picture element,” the tiny, dotlike units into which a video display is split. In medium resolution, your PC screen is made up of 200 by 320 pixels. Many NAPLPS decoders pro-duce a display with 200 by 2S6 pixels.

Bit map: Depending on the particular display system, each pixel in the display is represented by a specific number of bits in memory. In the simplest case (black and white), each pixel occupies one bit, which can be either on (white) or off (black). In color display, each pixel requires two or more bits, which repre-sent either the values of red, green, and blue to be generated for that pixel or an index into a color table (see “color map-ping" below). The display can be changed by changing these bits in mem-ory. This chunk of memory is the bit map. 

Video displays are sometimes de-scribed in terms of the number of vertical and horizontal pixels and the number of bits allotted to each pixel; for example, 200 X 320 X 2 (in the case of the PC’s medium resolution mode) or 2(X) x 256 X 4 (for many common NAPLPS decoder di^lays).

Color mapping: Color monitors cre-ate all their colors by combining various amounts of red, green, and blue at each pixel . In one pt^ar method for creating video displays, the display logic reads the amounts of red, green, and blue directly from the bits assigned to each pixel. Thus, in a 200 by 256 by 3 bit map, each of the three bits assigned to a pixel might be associated with one of the three basic colors. Depending on which of the three bits are on, the display logic can produce one of eight colors.

In another method, though, the bits assigned to each pixel do not actually represent red, green, and blue. Instead, the bits form a number which is a pointer into a color table or map. In our 200 x 256 X 3 bit map, for example, the bits assigned to each pixel can contain a number from 0 to 7. This number refers to an entry or slot in a color map. When the video display logic reads the bit val-ues associated with a pixel, it looks into the color table for the actual bits that define the relative values of red, green, and blue. This colw table contains eight entries, each of which may use, say, 12 bits for color definition. Thus, while we can still only display 8 different colors simultaneously, each of these colors can be defined by one of 4,096 different combinations of red, green, and blue.

And when we want to change the col-or of a large block of pixels on the screen, we don’t have to change the val-ues of all the associated bits in the bit map. We merely modify the bits which define the color in the particular colo*-map slot; this will cause all pbtels which point to this slot to change color. NAPLPS uses this ability to change col-or-map entries at high speed to create special effects, like animation and sequential (phased) blinking.

Frame: One screenful of graphics. Sometimes called a “page.”

Videotex: A system of large databases which can be accessed by many remote users from terminals, usually over telephone lines. Some videotex sys-tems are mainly textual (such as Compu-Serve), while others contain graphics (Viewtron or Grassroots, for example).

Telesoftware: Some videotex opera-tors have tried mixing NAPLPS code with actual binary program code. The program code is intercepted by the local terminal and executed instead of being displayed on the screen. The program code is called telesoftware.

PDIs: Picture Description Instruc-tions are the NAPLPS graphics codes that describe parts of graphics pictures, such as “rectangle” or “line.”

DRCS: Dynamically Redefinable Character Sets. A NAPLPS artist can create up to 96 customized characters which can be loaded into the decoder and then called from memory.

Macro: To save transmission time, a frequently used string of NAPLPS can be assigned a one-character name. Nine-ty six of these “macros” can be created and downloaded to the decoder. From then on, the string can be called from the decoder’s memtxy over and over again sinqily by supplying the macro’s name.

* Groping through the Basics *

Picture Painter is not as easy to leam as it should be. It takes a lot of nerve to ask $3,000 for software aixl then charge an extra $S0 for inadequate documentation. The documentation consists of a 7-page typewritten installation guide (which woiks) aixl a hefty “Picture Painter Ref-erence Guide.” The reference guide is aptly named. Relying on it to leam how to use the system is a bit like trying to leam a language ftom a dictionary. No tutorial is provided, and there is no introduction either to NAPLPS or Picture Painter. And the reference guide constantly refers you to a missing “Advanced Techniques” section. Cableshare is aware of the prob-lem; a customer support representative told me nxist clients need a day or two of training by a Cableshare insbuctor. To its credit, the reference guide is well written and organized. And, once you know the basics, it can be very valuable.

Cableshare supplies a colorful acetate overlay for your bit pad. The upper part of the overlay is marked into a grid which corresponds to the dimensions of the dis-play monitor. When you move the elec-tronic pen over the acetate, a crosshair cur-sor scoots acrtrss the screen. The lower part of the overlay is split into 164 small squares, each labeled with a function such as “rectangle” or “set color,” which you select by {jessing the pen to the square. All graphics-creation functions, from drawing circles to changing the color of a polygon, can be executed from the tablet. You can even enter text into the display from the tablet, since the squares in the lower left contain characters in a QWERTY layout. All operations can be performed from the IBM keyboard, too. This is valuable, since some functions, insetting a siring of text into your picture, for example, ate done much mote quickly from the key-board than from the tablet. Drawing graphics, though, is usually more efficient from the tablet.

When I first started Picture Painter, 1 thought it had crashed. My color monitor was connected to a decoder, which was connected to the COMl:PORT, displayed a Cableshaie logo at the bottom of the screen. And the PC’s monochrome moni-tor (or die Compaq’s internal monitor, in my case) showed nothing except for the word: Cursor 1 0. No menu, no help screen, nothing. The “Help” square caught my eye, so I attacked it with the pen. “Help with what?” We’ll start slow-ly, 1 thought, so 1 pressed the “Rectan-gle” box. “No help available for that box.” OK, we’ll try “Circle.” Same response. Continuing boldly onward, then, I tried the “Rectangle” square and hoped for the best. Aha! The word rect-angle appeared at the bottom of my color monitor. Aftera litde experimentation and a peek at the “Rectangle” section of the reference guide, I found that rectangles are drawn by moving the pen/cursor to the spot on the tablet/screen where you want one corner of the rectangle to appear. You press down and then move to the spot where you want the diagonally opposite corner to appear and press again. Voila! A solid white rectangle flashed on the screen.

The principle applies to all the NAPLPS primitives. Picture Painter will draw arcs, lines, points, polygons, and circles. You simply supply the minimum coordinates to define the outline of the shape you want. The software draws the rest. Once you understand the principle, it's a snap to fill your screen with wild, varied shapes. If solid white objects bore you, you can change fill patterns and colors. The “Tex-ture Pattern” square lets you pick one of four default fill patterns: solid, vertical lines, horizontal lines, and crosshatch. (You can even customize fill patterns if your decoder supports this NAPLPS fea-ture.) All subsequently drawn rectangles, arcs, circles, and polygons will fill up with the pattern you select. You can turn off all fill patterns if you just want to see out-lines.

* Color by Numbers *

Color selection is fun. Picture Painter allows you to pick from 16 different color slots, labeled 0 to 15. When you start the system, each of the 16 slots is assigned a default color, like red, green, blue, magenta, or various shades of gray. Each color slot has its own box on the tablet, which shows its number and the default color assigned to it. To pick red, say, you just press the pen to the red box. From then on, everything you draw will be ted. Press the pen to another box to switch col-ors. You are not limited to the 16 default colors. You can define 4,096 colors with Picture Painter (though some decoders can only handle 512) and assign your choices to the 16 slots.

Picture Painter stands out from the competition when it comes to defining a color. You can choose from six different ways of creating, say, a flesh tone. First you make the basic choice of whether you want to deHne colors based on the relative values of red, green, and blue in the final color (the RGB method) or the relative amounts of hue, saturation, and value (the HSV method). Each method has its adher-ents among artists, and it is to Picture Painter's credit that both are available.

You select one of the 16 color slots to modify and press the “Set Color” square. A small rectangle appears at the bottom of your screen showing the current color attached to the color slot you have chosen. If you slide the pen around the tablet, the color in the small rectangle will shift, as will any objects on the screen drawn with that color slot. The tablet is ingeniously organized into three axes (two vertical and one horizontal), each repre-senting a red, green, or blue (or HSV) scale. Once you have mixed the color you want, you assign it to the color slot by pressing the pen to the tablet. A message appears on the screen telling you the numeric values in the range 0 to 255 of each of the three components — either RGB or HSV — of your new color.

You can also mix a color with the PC’s numeric keypad, which is organized into three columns. The 7 and 1 keys, for example, increase and decrease the red component, the 8 and 2 keys change the green, and the 9 and 3 keys shift the blue value. The 5 key is used to enter the final color mix. Finally, if you need to mix a color exactly, you can type in the actual num-bers of each of the three components from the keyboard.

These kinds of color map manipula-tions can produce startling effects. NAPLPS interpreters tend to display com-plex shapes rather slowly, but it is possible to make graphics flash onto the screen in an instant with the help of color map changes. As a simple example, 1 filled the screen with a black rectangle. Next, 1 defined yet another color slot to be black and, with this color, drew a large, com-plex polygon. The polygon was invisible, since it blended into the background. Finally, I entered commands to set this second black color slot to yellow. When the page displayed, I could not see the polygon build in the typical, slow NAPLPS manner (since it was black on black background). But suddenly, after it had been built, the polygon’s color slot changed to yellow. In a split second, the polygon popped onto the screen.

Picture Painter can generate nearly every kind of NAPLPS code. This is quite an accomplishment, given the hundreds of graphics commands included in the stan-dard. In fact, I found only a few features not implemented: relative coordinates, incremental point, line, and polygon, and “domain” definition (used to create graphics for decoders with a resolution higher than 200 by 256). These are hardly serious omissions. And as frosting. Pic-ture Painter comes with a slew of snazzy fonts, so you can display your text in script, Helvetica, roman, fraktur and sev-eral other variations. (Cableshare also offers a DRCS editor that runs outside of Picture Painter and lets the artist create custom character sets. I was not able to test this program.)

* Editing in Pseudo-NAPLPS *

Cableshare adopted an interesting and unique method for editing graphics. NAPLPS code consists of a string of bytes, which the decoder interprets sequentially. The decoder displays image after image as the bytes are received and decoded. The concept is not much different from a string of ASCII characters that your computer interprets and displays on the screen, one at a time. It would even be possible for the masochistically inclined to use a word processor to create an appro-priate string of NAPLPS code which, if sent to an interpreter, would produce graphic images.

Most NAPLPS creation software tries hard to hide the NAPLPS code from the user. When an object, say, a rectangle, is to be edited, the user selects it by moving the cursor onto the subject. Picture Painter, however, asks you to edit the actual NAPLPS commands rather than the screen images they produce. As you produce a page. Picture Painter trans-lates your commands into a sequence of pseudo-NAPLPS statements, such as “Set Color 2” or “Rectangle 10 25 180 212.” When it displays your page. Picture Painter is actually reading through this sequence of command statements and exe-cuting them one by one. When you edit a graphic, you actually edit one or mote of these pseudo-NAPLPS statements. And when Picture Painter writes a graphic file to disk , it actually writes a series of lines of pseudo-NAPLPS.

* Picture Painter asks you to edit the actual NAPLPS commands rather than the screen images they produce. *

While 1 found this approach to graphics creation clumsy at first, I am now a con-vert. This pseudo-NAPLPS language, dubbed CGUL (pronounced see-gull) for Cableshare Graphics User Language, of-fers features not available in other page creation systems. First, when you want to display a frame, you have the option of stepping through it one statement at a time. As you do this, the CGUL statement appears at the bottom of your screen, while the graphic named in the statement is drawn on the screen. You can even step backwards through a file! And you can insert comment lines into the CGUL code, which can be a great help when you try to modify a complex page that was created months ago.

To edit a graphic — for example, to change a red circle into a blue one — you step through the frame until you find the offending “Circle” statement. (In a large graphic file, you can even use a search command to jump straight to each of the “Circle" statements.) Then you press the “Insert” square and select blue from the tablet. The next time you display that frame, the circle will be blue. You can even edit a series of com-mands at once by defining them as a block, which can be moved, copied, rotat-ed, and displayed.

The primary drawback to Cableshare’s CGUL invention is that the graphics files that Picture Painter stores to disk are not real NAPLPS. In fact, you must convert each file using a translation program before you can display the graphics on any system other than a Picture Painter. As a result, you end up with two disk files for each page. And if you ever plan to re-edit your page, you must save the CGUL ver-sion, since Picture Pairuer cannot edit raw NAPLPS code. (Cableshare provides a NAPLPS-to-CGUL translator, but I’ve had mixed results with the flies it produces, some of which contain weird garbage. A customer support representa-tive admitted the program has bugs.)

* Checks and Balances *

In spite of this problem, I prefer Cableshare's CGUL approach. Seeing the actual commands in addition to the images they produce, has a great pedagogical value. I imagine artists trained on Picture Painter will have an easy time understanding and using the complex, powerful features of NAPLPS, such as macros, color mapping, and blink-based animation. Picture Painting does a superb job of keeping self-destructive users at bay. All potentially destructive commands — such as erasing the screen or overwriting a pre-existing file — require confirmation before they execute.

The customer service folks at Cable-share were helpful and reasonably well informed when I pestered them with ques-tions about Picture Painter. My only bad experience occurred when I tried to report the one bug I have found. No matter how careful I was to press the electronic pen firmly down in the center of the proper square. Picture Painter occasionally shot back spurious messages or simply did not respond at all. I asked two graphic artists who have used Picture Painter about this, and both confirm the problem. Yet both a hardware engineer and a customer support rep at Cableshare told me the “bug” was my fault and that I should be more careful about where I put the pen. Uh-oh.

Picture Painter is a good product. With the addition of some extra hardware, it can turn your PC into a NAPLPS graphics cre-ation station as powerful as stand alone systems costing many times more. Given better documentation and training materi-al, Picture Painter would be simple enough for the occasional artist, yet pow-erful enough for the NAPLPS pro.


** VAST: A Videotex Application System **

You’ve arrived. You have the classiest graphics on the block, guaranteed to knock the socks off your boss, your clients, your mother, and anyone else you can get to look at them. Ah, there’s the rub. How do you get them to look? You can’t just saunter into the board room and hand the wolves a disk and a PC. You need an easy, seductive way for your audience to get the message.

VAST does the trick. This package turns your PC into a single or multiuser NAPLPS videotex system. The basic idea is that your PC is a videotex host that serves videotex decoders connected to its communication ports. The end-user sits in front of a decoder/ monitor with a keypad/ keyboard and winds through a database of linked NAPLPS frames. The system oper-ator (yes, you) organizes the frames and establishes the links.

The burden of setting up a fun, easy-to-use database tests on your shoulders. If you do a good job, the end-user has only to sit back, watch the graphics, and press an occasional button on the keypad. My 2-year-old son even got into the act.

Were it not for a couple of major omis-sions in the software, VAST would be an ideal tool for creating interactive business presentations, in-house information, train-ing databases, advertising-supported pub-lic videotex systems for shopping malls, hotels, airports, and so on. Even as it stands, though, VAST is a useful prxxiuct that provides a great excuse for jumping on the NAPLPS wagon.

* Inscrutable Functions *

The hard part is learning how to use VAST. While its manufacturer, Tayson, did have the courtesy to provide a half-page overview of the software in the manual, it neglected to explain the fundamen-tal principle behind its database organiza-tion scheme. Without this understanding, VASTi three primary functions, frame display, database management, and frame creation, are pretty inscmtable.

It took me and a couple of friends a half-hour of tentative button-pushing and leafing through the manual to divine the basic principle. VAST deals only with two entities: databases and frames. Frames must be part of a database, and they are numbered from 1 to 32,767. There is no way to access or create a frame that’s not contained in a database.

The implication is that VAST will not allow a user to directly access a DOS file. In other words. ■! caruiot copy NAPLPS DOS files onto my VAST data disk and then access them from VAST. Incredibly, the only ways to get flames into a VAST database are either to create them inside VAST using a relatively primitive frame-creation system or to crank up VAST s data capture feature to grab frames sent in over one of the asynch ports. In other words, if you create your pages on Picture Painter, you can’t just grab them off the data disk and insert them into a VAST database. And once you make a VAST frame, there is no way to get it out of I/AST's internal database format and write it directly to disk as a plain vanilla DOS file that you could edit with, say. Picture Painter. In fact, if you don’t like VAST'S unsophisticated frame creator, your only option is to connect two computers via the asynch ports. Only then could you send pages back and forth between VAST and the outside world.

1 found this so bizarre that I refused to believe it. Not until 1 called the company for help did 1 discover I didn’t need help, just different software. (I imagine the problem is a remnant of the days a year or so ago when there were no page-creation systems for the PC. In those days, the only way to get any NAPLPS file onto a DOS disk was via file transfer from a stand-alone page-creation system.) Tayson pres-ident Peter Richardson says he has heard this complaint from other users. A spokes-person reported that the problem has been eliminated in the currently available ver-sion.

Once I accepted the world according to VAST, things went better. VAST provides three ways to view frames, each of which pumps the NAPLPS to an external NAPLPS decoder. First, the system oper-ator can sit at the PC keyboard and display individual frames over one of the asynch ports. Second, you can define a sequence of frames — say, frames I thnxigh 25 under database “Business” — and have VAST display them one after another in a never-ending cycle. Finally, you can jump into one of your linked databases and relinquish control to the end-user at the remote decoder, who can navigate from frame to frame based on menu selections you provide during database creation.

* Defining a NAPLPS Database *

Defining a new database is straightfor-ward. VAST is menu-driven, and my only complaint is that some of the menu choices are needlessly cryptic. To make or modify new databases, for instance, you pick either “Create/Modify Frame Pa-rameter Block” or “Create/Modify Frame Destination Table” from the main menu. Why not “Setup Database” and “Link Database Pages”?

When you create a database, you spec-ify communications parameters for the comm line you want the database to use. You can enter a short description of the database. If you want to “billboard” frames (that is, those displayed in a cyclic, automatic mode), you specify which range of frames to billboard and the number of seconds the system should pause between each frame (this interval carmot vary from frame to frame). VAST can also put a dig-ital clock of varying sizes and colors on each billboard frame; you define the size, color, and location of the clock.

* Not until I called the company for help did I discover I didn’t need help, just different software. *

VAST has a clever variation on the billboard theme. When you crank up a database on a comm line, you can tell VAST to go into a temporary billboard mode while it waits for a passerby to start pressing keys. This is much better than just having a static title page staring out into space when the system is not being used. In a shopping mall, for example, VAST might billboard a series of eye-catching ads whenever it is not being used interactively by passersby. You tell VAST which frames to cycle through when in this automatic mode. And you can define which key you want the user to hit to interrupt the billboard and jump into the interactive database. And finally, you specify the number of minutes and seconds you want VAST to lie dormant before it restarts the billboard. Thus, if a user walks away from the system in the middle of the database, VAST will automatically reset itself 1 amused myself one evening by setting up a database and timing the billboard functions with a stopwatch. Everything worked out right to the second.

* Frame Creation *

Once you set up the database parameters, you need to get some frames. One option is to create them from scratch. VAST has an unsophisticated but easy-to-use frame creator. You can use all the NAPLPS geometric primitives in 15 colors and shades of gray. Frames can contain graphics and text, and they can be recalled from a database for later modification.

Serious artists will miss color mapping and other sophisticated NAPLPS features like macros, DRCS, and phase blink. But for many business applications, particularly presentations or training systems, the frame creator should be adequate. VAST includes a curious so-called “Text Editor” that allows you to display and edit the string of NAPLPS bytes that make up a frame. (This is not pseudo-NAPLPS like Cableshare’s CGUL, but actual NAPLPS bytes.) First, fiddling with NAPLPS this way makes about as much sense as writing programs with DEBUG. It may be a neat macho trick, but it sure isn’t very efficient. And VASTs editor makes EDLIN look good by comparison.

* Capturing Frames *

VAST can also capture NAPLPS frames from other computers. You have two options. In the one case you connect your VAST PC to another computer via an RS-232 cable. VAST opens its capture buffer, and you then enter the appropriate commands on the other machine in order to send a stream of bytes to VAST. When all bytes have been sent, you assign the new data a frame number and VAST inseits it into the currently open database. Since I only had one micro in my office, I couldn't test this feature.

Data from a remote NAPLPS database, such as Grassroots, can also be captured with VAST. This requires two asynch ports: one connected to your modem, and another to your decoder. When you start, VAST lets you dial a phone number from your PC keyboard. As soon as you connect, VAST begins passing all remote input to the decoder and requires that all local input come from the decoder’s keypad. You are now using your decoder to talk to the remote database, though all data passes through the PC as well. VASTbuff-ers all bytes that flow into the PC. At any time you can enter a simple command on the decoder keypad which VAST will intercept and interpret as a command to write all buffered data into a frame and to empty the capture buffer. The program is amusing and easy, and I captured 10 frames from Grassroots in just a few minutes.

Once your database contains frames, you can set up the relationships between Ihem. You can specify, for example, that pressing the 3 key while displaying frame 27 should jump the user to frame 45. Or you might define the less than (<) key to mean “go to the previously accessed page.” VAST offers an unusually rich repertoire of key definitions, and you can cre-ate a large database of almo.st limitless complexity. Fortunately, the screen display that prompts you for this linking information is marvelously clear. I had no trouble setting up all kinds of cross references between frames. And VAST will display on your screen or in a printout a nicely formatted table for each frame, describing the definition of each keypad key with respect to that frame.

* The screen display that prompts you for linking database information is marvelously clear. *

Other than the problems mentioned earlier (no access to DOS files and no tutorial), the only other serious problem is VAST'S inability to log user activity. When VAST" is used for business presentations, it may not be important to know how many times and when each frame was accessed. But whenever VAST is used to display advertisements, both the advertisers and the system operator need to measure usage. It would be a more useful product if it kept a constant disk-based log of all activity.

I have yet not been able to test VAST's performance on large databases since Tay-son’s review copy intentionally limited me to one database with no more than 15 different pages. Otherwise, the version that 1 tested was a fully functional single-user system.

Tayson also offers upgrades for two to eight users. The simplest form of two-user system simply requires two asynch ports, decoders, and monitors. Both users must access the same database, though they can display pages independently. With the addition of MultiLink software and a Hostess 8-port expansion card, Tayson claims VAST will handle up to eight independent users, each of whom can access a separate database. None of the multiuser configurations were tested.


David McCune is president of The Proteus Group, Inc., a New York videotex consulting firm.


* Product Information *

Finding out more about the products reviewed in this article may require a call to Canada. 

* Microstar Videotex Interpreter (MVl) *
	Microstar Software, Ltd. 
	2211 Riverside Dr., Suite 207 
	Ottawa, Ontario 
	Canada KIH 7X5 
	(613) 737-9630 
	List Price: $240 

	Requires: 192K RAM, one 320K disk drive, IBM color adapter or Plantronics COLORPLUS card, color monitor, one asynchronous conununications adapter, modem. 

	CIRCLE 701 ON READER SERVICE CARD

* Quickpel *
	David Carlisle & Associates 
	235 Yorkland Blvd., Suite 300 
	Willowdale, Ontario 
	Canada M2J 4Y8 
	(416) 492-9803 
	List Price: $625 

	Requires: DOS 2.0, color monitor, modem. 

	CIRCLE 702 ON READER SERVICE CARD 

* Picture Painter *
	Cableshare, Inc. 
	P.O. Box 5880 
	London, Ontario 
	Canada N6A 4L7 
	(519) 686-2900 

	List Price: Software, $3,000; documentation, $50 

	Requires: 128K RAM, one 320K disk drive, color monitor, two asynchronous conununications adapters, Summagraphics’ Bit Pad One tablet, stand alone NAPLPS decoder. 

	CIRCLE 703 ON READER SERVICE CARD

* VAST (Videotex Application System by Tayson) *
	Tayson Information Technology, Inc. 
	275 Comstock Road 
	Scarborough, Ontario 
	Canada MIL 2H2 
	(416) 288-0550 

	List Price: Single-user system, $1,000 (Canadian); 
	each additional user (maximum 8), $420

	Requires: For a single-user system, two disk drives, COMl: and COM2: ports, 128K RAM (with DOS 1.1) or 192K RAM (with DOS 2.0). 
	For a two-user system, 256K RAM is required. 

	Recommended: Two double-sided disk drives, 256K RAM. 

	CIRCLE 704 ON READER SERVICE CARD 